Register of the Hughes-Ware Family Papers 1836-1933
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Hughes-Ware Family Papers, 1836-1933
Library of Virginia
37961
3.3 cubic feet
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Purchased from Michael Silverman, Newport News, Virginia, 5 December 2000
Biographical/Historical Information
The Hughes and Ware families were residents of Gloucester County and Richmond, Virginia. Henry Hughes (ca. 1806-1854) married Mary E.D. Hall (ca. 1820-1897). Their daughter Mary Elizabeth Hughes was born on 11 March 1838 and died 12 October 1912. She married Cincinnatus J. Ware (1839-1864), and together they settled in Richmond. He died while serving in the 5th Virginia Cavalry during the Civil War. They had three children, William Henry Ware (b. 1860), Cincinnatus J. Ware (b. 1862), and Marion Lee Ware (b. 1865). Marion Lee Ware married Ella Stuart Cooke (b. ca. 1871) on 30 January 1896. Their daughter Ella Booth Ware was born in 1897.
Scope and Content Information
Papers, 1836-1933, of the Hughes and Ware families of Gloucester County and Richmond, Virginia. Includes correspondence, subject files, and oversized items.
SERIES DESCRIPTION
Series I: Correspondence
The correspondence covers the years 1848 to 1933. Topics include family news, schooling, the courtship of Mary E. Hughes and Cincinnatus Ware, social life, recreational activities, the health of family members and acquaintances, and births, marriages, and deaths of various individuals. Much of the pre-Civil War correspondence is between Mary E.D. Hughes of Gloucester County and her daughter Mary E. Ware of Richmond. Also of interest is the Civil War correspondence of Cincinnatus Ware and his brother William S. Ware while they were serving in the 5th Virginia Cavalry. Subjects include troop movements, the taking of prisoners, battles and skirmishes around Fredericksburg, Winchester, Culpeper Courthouse, Shepardstown,and Caroline and Spotsylvania Counties. There are also letters concerning the death of Cincinnatus Ware at Newtown in 1864.
Series II: Subject Files
The subject files contain accounts, clippings, deeds, envelopes, financial records, guardian's accounts, legal papers, memorandum and account books, prommissory notes, receipts, including rental receipts for oyster grounds and tax receipts, and other material. There is also material relating to the 5th Virginia Cavalry, including an affidavit, appointment, a list of money loaned and due William S. Ware while in camp, a morning report, muster roll, and order for detail.
Series III. Oversized Items
The oversized items contain accounts, including guardian's accounts, as well as two horse pedigrees, and membership applications.
Contents List
- Correspondence, 1848-1924, 1933, n.d.
  - Correspondence, 1848-1853 (Box-folder Box 1 Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1857 (Box-folder Box 1 Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1858 (January-August) (Box-folder Box 1 Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1858 (September-December) (Box-folder Box 1 Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1859 (January-July) (Box-folder Box 1 Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1859 (August-December) (Box-folder Box 1 Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1860 (Box-folder Box 1 Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1861 (Box-folder Box 1 Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1862 (Box-folder Box 1 Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1863 (Box-folder Box 1 Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1854 (Box-folder Box 1 Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1865-1869 (Box-folder Box 1 Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1870-1875 (Box-folder Box 1 Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1876-1879 (Box-folder Box 1 Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1880 (Box-folder Box 2 Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1881 (Box-folder Box 2 Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1882 (Box-folder Box 2 Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1883 (Box-folder Box 2 Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1884 (Box-folder Box 2 Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1885 (Box-folder Box 2 Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1886 (Box-folder Box 2 Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1887 (January-June) (Box-folder Box 2 Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1887 (July-December) (Box-folder Box 2 Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1888 (January-June) (Box-folder Box 2 Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1888 (July-December) (Box-folder Box 2 Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1889 (Box-folder Box 2 Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1890 (Box-folder Box 2 Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1891-1892 (Box-folder Box 2 Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1893-1897 (Box-folder Box 2 Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1898-1899 (Box-folder Box 2 Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1900 (Box-folder Box 2 Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1901 (Box-folder Box 2 Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1902 (January-June) (Box-folder Box 3 Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1902 (July-December) (Box-folder Box 3 Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1903 (Box-folder Box 3 Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1904-1090 (Box-folder Box 3 Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1910-1912 (Box-folder Box 3 Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1913-1918 (Box-folder Box 3 Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1919 (January, June) (Box-folder Box 3 Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1919 (September-October) (Box-folder Box 3 Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1919 (November 1-15) (Box-folder Box 3 Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1919 (November 16-30) (Box-folder Box 3 Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1919 (December) (Box-folder Box 3 Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1920 (January) (Box-folder Box 3 Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1920 (February-March) (Box-folder Box 3 Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1920 (April-May) (Box-folder Box 3 Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1920 (June, September) (Box-folder Box 3 Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1921 (Box-folder Box 3 Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1922 (Box-folder Box 3 Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1923 (Box-folder Box 3 Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1924 (Box-folder Box 3 Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1933 (Box-folder Box 3 Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, n.d. (Henry Hughes) (Box-folder Box 4 Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, n.d. (Mary E.D. Hughes) (Box-folder Box 4 Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, n.d. (Catherine S. Smith) (Box-folder Box 4 Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, n.d. (Mary E. Ware) (Box-folder Box 4 Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, n.d. (Lucy Lee Montague Wiatt) (Box-folder Box 4 Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, n.d. (Civil War) (Box-folder Box 4 Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, n.d. (Various Individuals) (Box-folder Box 4 Folders 7-9)
- Subject Files
  - Accounts (Box-folder Box 5 Folder 1)
  - Affidavit re: C.J. Ware's Horse, 15 February 1865 (Box-folder Box 5 Folder 2)
  - Appointment, C.J. Ware as 2nd Lt., Co.A, 5th Va. Cavalry, 18 April 1864 (Box-folder Box 5 Folder 3)
  - Cancelled Checks, Deposit Slips, Statements (Box-folder Box 5 Folder 4)
  - Clippings (Box-folder Box 5 Folder 5)
  - Deeds 1883-1906 (Box-folder Box 5 Folder 6)
  - Dog License Cards, 1923-1925 (Box-folder Box 5 Folder 7)
  - Envelopes (Box-folder Box 5 Folders 8-12)
  - Essays (Box-folder Box 5 Folder 13)
  - Estate papers of Henry Hughes (Box-folder Box 5 Folders 14)
  - Fabric Swatches (Box-folder Box 5 Folders 15)
  - Fifty Cent Note 1861 (Box-folder Box 5 Folder 16)
  - Fragments (Box-folder Box 5 Folders 17)
  - Guardian's Accounts (Mary E. Hughes) (Box-folder Box 5 Folders 18)
  - Guardian's Accounts (Augustine S. Hughes) (Box-folder Box 5 Folders 19)
  - Guardian's Accounts (Henry Hughes) (Box-folder Box 5 Folders 20)
  - Guardian's Accounts (Laura Lee Hughes) (Box-folder Box 5 Folders 21)
  - Final Guardianship Acount 1873 (Box-folder Box 5 Folder 22)
  - Miscellaneous Guardian's Accounts (Box-folder Box 5 Folders 23)
  - Hair (Box-folder Box 5 Folders 24)
  - Internal Revenue Tax Stamps 1877 (Box-folder Box 5 Folder 25)
  - Legal Papers (Box-folder Box 5 Folders 26)
  - License Applications (Box-folder Box 5 Folders 27)
  - List of Delinquent Real Estate, Gloucester County 1886 (Box-folder Box 5 Folder 28)
  - Memorandum and Account Books (Box-folder Box 6 Folders 1-3)
  - Military Passes, 1864 (Box-folder Box 6 Folder 4)
  - Militia Fine, 1859 (Box-folder Box 6 Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box-folder Box 6 Folders 6-8)
  - Money Loaned and Due to William S. Ware While in Camp, 1863 (Box-folder Box 6 Folder 9)
  - Morning Report, Co. A, 5th Va. Cavalry, 1864 (Box-folder Box 6 Folder 10)
  - Muster Roll, Co. A, 5th Va. Cavalry, n.d. (Box-folder Box 6 Folder 11)
  - Order for Detail, 4 October 1864 (Box-folder Box 6 Folder 12)
  - Pension Applications (Box-folder Box 6 Folders 13)
  - Photographs (Box-folder Box 6 Folders 14)
  - Poetry (Box-folder Box 6 Folders 15)
  - Prescriptions (Box-folder Box 6 Folders 16)
  - Promissory Notes, 1841-1924 (Box-folder Box 6 Folder 17)
  - Receipts, 1841-1924 (Box-folder Box 7 Folders 1-10)
  - Receipts, n.d. (Box-folder Box 7 Folder 11)
  - Recipes (Box-folder Box 7 Folder 12)
  - Rental Receipts for Oyster Grounds (Box-folder Box 7 Folder 13)
  - School Report Cards (Box-folder Box 7 Folder 14)
  - Survey Field Notes (Box-folder Box 7 Folder 15)
  - Tax Receipts, 1856-1923 (Box-folder Box 7 Folders 16-23)
  - Wedding Invitations (Box-folder Box 7 Folder 24)
- Oversized Items
  - Accounts (Box-folder Box 8 Folder 1)
  - Guardian's Accounts, 1858-1862 (Box-folder Box 8 Folder 2)
  - Horse Pedigrees (Box-folder Box 8 Folder 3)
  - Provident Relief Association of Washington, DC, Certificate of Membership, 1916 (Box-folder Box 8 Folder 4)
  - Royal Templars of Temperance Applications (blank) (Box-folder Box 8 Folder 5)